[Music]
there's a great variety of symptoms
suffered by women undergoing menopause
they're the so-called vasomotor symptoms
like
night sweats and hot flashes difficulty
sleeping or full-on insomnia vaginal
dryness and pain during sex as well as
adverse effects on mood including
full-blown depression
might exercise help exercise can
certainly help with physical and
psychological quality of life in general
but unfortunately there's no evidence
for the effects of exercise and
menopause specific symptoms
you know researchers are getting
desperate when they try to see if giving
people big placenta will help
spoiler alert
it doesn't
well we know oxidative stress which is a
consequence of excessive free oxygen
radicals or impaired antioxidant defense
is linked not only to diseases such as
diabetes obesity cardiovascular disease
but also menopausal symptoms like hot
flashes
low free oxygen radical defenses
associated with more menopausal symptoms
just like having a diet with more
antioxidants is associated with fewer
menopausal symptoms
in fact a high intake of fruits and
vegetables may delay the onset of
menopause in the first place thought to
be because the presence of antioxidants
in fruits and vegetables may counteract
the adverse effects of free radicals and
the number and functional eggs you still
have in your ovaries whereas the reason
high meat consumption has been related
to degenerative diseases may not just be
the saturated fat and cholesterol but
the pro-oxidation products generated
during their production
storage digestion and the metabolism of
meat
similarly since a pro-inflammatory diet
has also been associated with higher
menopause specific somatic symptoms
meaning like hot flashes and sleep
issues
that would mean moving towards a more
plant-based diet packed with
anti-inflammatory components like fiber
and away from pro-inflammatory foods
containing saturated fat and cholesterol
no wonder whole plant foods intake has
been associated with fewer menopausal
symptoms
in terms of specific foods
poultry and skim dairy products may be
particularly bad whereas soy milk seemed
to help
so women may derive benefit from lower
consumption of poultry and skimmed dairy
and a greater consumption of vegetables
than soy milk
you don't really know though until you
put it to the test and indeed women
randomized to drink soy milk reduce
their menopausal symptoms by 20
within 12 weeks
no wonder that those eating strictly
plant-based diets report less bothersome
menopausal symptoms among women
undergoing menopause vegans reported
less bothersome symptoms and within the
diet groups more vegetables and in the
meat-eating group less flesh food was
associated with less bothersome symptoms
as well so eating a plant-based diet may
be helpful for women in their menopausal
transition who prefer a natural means to
manage their symptoms consistent with
all the other studies demonstrating
reduced menopausal symptoms in those
consuming greater quantities of
plant-based foods and less meat
but again
maybe there are other reasons healthier
eaters have fewer symptoms you can't
prove cause and
effect until
you guessed it an interventional trial
to see if changing your diet actually
reduces symptoms and in this study where
women were encouraged to decrease fat
and increase fruit vegetable and whole
grain intake they were significantly
more likely to eliminate their vasomotor
symptoms like hot flashes and night
sweats compared to the control group so
it's
certainly not all or nothing and within
a plant-based diet those randomized to a
meat-free diet with daily flaxseed oil
walnuts and almonds did better than
those randomized to the same diet but
with daily extra virgin olive oil after
16 weeks the vegetarian diet that was
rich in omega-3s did better reducing
vasomotor symptom frequency in fact even
just two teaspoons worth of ground
flaxseeds a day alone can significantly
decrease menopausal symptoms to about
the same extent as hormone replacement
therapy but without the side effects
[Music]
you